right emphasize is all right what
happens when we don't make that
distinction set up consequences yeah it
has the kinds of consequences of like
how you respond to the right now I
respond in the right right it has
something to do with the quality of my
experience in the quality of my
experience is the thing that actually
when I think about it is the thing that
has me go I'm having a good life I'm
having a bad life or a good day or a bad
day it's the thing I most care about in
fact it's impossible not to care about
that right if you're a human being so
but let's look at this example here's a
box is the boss don't do
okay so are you seeing the box as if
you're looking from underneath it yeah
can you see the box as if you're looking
from above it I guess if you're like
kind of looking up from this angle
everyone look at the box I'm seeing it
as though I is closed it uh-huh this
side is closest yeah what if this side
was closest and this side was farthest
this was the front this was a bang what
if this one was the bottom and you're
looking underneath it which one's of
them this right here this is the bottom
right that's what I'm seeing that is the
bottom ok cool so now let's say this is
the top can you see it was like the top
can you in other words can you have
you have you been able to see it in
different ways oh so imagine all right
sufficient it's imagine like you're
looking up at it like this right this
corner right is the top right and then I
would just open the box right like that
see ya exactly right I got that one oh
you already had that one yeah ok so
let's erase that um just to make
everyone else feel really smart yes yes
totally so and you saw this is about
like you're looking down up at it right
oh now I see see ya oh oh oh and as
you're looking I you know it's I hope
you can't let me see can you see that
yeah that's Clark man that's clear I'm
just gonna zoom in really quick just in
case see the box oops that is your world
the point I'm making what is the point
that I'm making that we're making we
call see we call this the way it is yet
it changes based on what you all saw it
change you can look at it from a zip is
looking this way or concur from you as
you're looking this way or from this way
or from underneath it's the same what
it's the same given right but how it
occurs for you changes right so how the
world shows up for me is given not by
what shows up but something I'm giving
to it what is that that I change that
has the box change or the occurring view
what is it that has the occurring future
yeah what did you change in yourself
that have the box occurred differently
to you that we normally call the way it
is my focus your focus right that speaks
to it what's another word can you in
order to change your focus all right so
your focus is just something you do with
your eyes what hand do you change your
focus I thought so your thoughts yeah
definitely huh did you change your
perspective
yeah totally perspective is one way of
saying so there's a lot of different
ways of saying it but have you noticed
ever noticed how any universe where the
only constant the only thing that's
always going on and never changes his
change that people and some of them may
be the one that is listening to my voice
including the one speaking have a
million jobs but always seem to end up
with the same boss or get married I know
somebody at some videos married 15 times
and it was after the 15th one that he
saw that he realized that he'd married
the same woman I took 15 yeah and it
wasn't until the 12th one till he
figured out that maybe it wasn't them
right or do you notice how some people
no matter what the circumstances they
find a way to have it that they don't
they're not liked or they're not seen or
they're not gotten right or some people
are more on the grantee Oh side of like
they they always occurs for them that um
everyone loves that right but if you
notice people do really have a
consistent way that they see if you know
them right so this now we're starting to
get at what is it that we give to the
given that determines the quality right
so make sure that's able to say that
yeah okay so one way of saying it is you
could say point of view
that's when what you could say you could
say your perspective right you can also
say how if you want to be more active
like more pervy about you can say how
you see right or if you want to be more
auditory about it you can say you're
listening right people of a certain
listening so all these things it's
interesting because if you really think
about it I can tie you up and I can take
away every freedom you have but the one
thing I can't take away from you is how
you see it yeah and how is how you see
it different from your occurring leave
you this is like I would look at it like
this like this is like the lens yeah and
this is the photo okay right if you want
to think about in terms of metaphor this
is the lens so if you want to see it
differently we always have the freedom
change lens right just like a change the
perspective I can take and literally
like like tie you up and yeah at perfect
example is Nelson Mandela hmm right in
prison if he saw what prison is this way
he made oh yeah I don't know the exact
story but he like he enrolled all the
guards and yes he changed from with in
prison right he that was given by how he
saw it because what couldn't be prisoned
is how he saw and how he saw was the
difference that made the difference
right it actually created an outcome
that changed the world right now but
what's interesting to me is that how
come like think about the people that
you know really well think about your
parents
your brothers and your sisters if people
oh you know really well don't you kind
of know where they're gonna vote for you
kind of can predict like there's certain
things you just won't talk to your
parents about because you already know
what they're going to say right um you
kind of know what movies are going to
like and not like you kind of know how
they'll respond to the point you count
Mosca mimic that what is that that you
know about them then have you be able to
know they're consistent way of seeing
such that you know how a certain
situation like a movie or president or
something like that will occur for them
that